<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Egmont Mika</title>
    <link>http://egmontmika.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Egmont Mika</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 03:01:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://egmontmika.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Start a Church</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/how-to-start-a-church-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/how-to-start-a-church-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to imagine that the only way to start a church is by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renting an auditorium,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging a speaker and a worship team,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gathering a crowd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, there is another way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need all of this, not even money. Instead of starting an organisation with a programme, you could rather think of igniting a process. And you can do this right where you are, wherever you live, work, study or spend your spare time. You start out by making just one disciple of Jesus. And then another one, and another. One or two at a time, maybe even a couple or a family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by your example, you teach these people to do the same with their relatives and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your home base is your kitchen table. This is where you gather, share your meals, pray, teach, mentor and empower those who want to join you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where everythings starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your area of operation is your social network, your family, relatives, friends and collgues. Moreover the city, its streets and squares, the parks, shopping centers, restaurants and cafés, the gyms and clubs… any place where you can meet people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sooner or later, there will be a fellowship of Jesus-followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem a lot easier, faster and more rewarding way to rent an auditorium, engage a speaker and a worship team and make enough noise to attract a crowd, then call it “church”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is, what Jesus would call it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - how would he do it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking a New Decision</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/taking-a-new-decision/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/taking-a-new-decision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s time for a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From time to time, following Jesus requires a new decision.
Why can it be so hard to take that decision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would it mean that your former decisions, traditions and habits, your arguments,
convictions and priorities become meaningless?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would it mean that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; was wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not necessarily. Probably, it all was right, based on the
information you had at that time. But now you know more. Now you have a
better understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you feel the need for a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what will you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will you let your tradition or habit or convenience be strong enough to override your desire
for a new and better decision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or will you give in to peer pressure of sticking with
your &amp;ldquo;tribe&amp;rdquo;, your relatives and friends or your group (&amp;ldquo;What will they say?&amp;rdquo;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, it takes humility and courage to make a new decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And trust in the voice of your heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noomi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or be afraid that people won&amp;rsquo;t take you serious because you&amp;rsquo;re not sticking to what
you built up and believed in and instead run off to something new and often more uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Egmont&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True. If you need much confirmation you better stay inside
the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kristina&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, sometimes God invites you to leave everything. We lived in the big city for about 10 years and have been the leaders of a small home church. However, we felt the need to leave it all and move into a small village with just a few people around. Hard to understand such a decision! But we feel so so happy and God already gave us a new church family with really honest and worm people who accepted us so lovingly. Change is good if it is led by God. Sometimes we feel like God already prepared and arranged things in advance and we just go and find it all arranged and set out waiting for us. He is such a provider!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Egmont&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Kristina!
Thank you for your comment. This sounds so right and good. Peace and joy follow those who are being led by the Spirit, no matter what the circumstances. And whenever the situation does not look so great, the family of the Lord stands out even greater. Making one or a few disciples, one by one, who can do the same with other people is the best we can do. No church program can ever match up to that. It’s quality that counts in the Kingdom, not numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kristina&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amen, thank you for your encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broken Trust</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/broken-trust-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 13:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/broken-trust-8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Broken trust is painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can be wonderful, but also give you a nightmare. Loving people includes the risk of getting hurt.
The more you love, the more vulnerable you get, the more pain you may have to suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worst of all, the suffering of broken trust. Suffering a life-long injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if you want to play safe, don’t get engaged with people. Don’t love, don’t care. Keep out of reach. Keep the mask. Play cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what kind of a life would that be!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not created as islands. We need each other. Need to care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That requires courage. So, let’s not get intimidated or scared by negative experiences. Instead, let&amp;rsquo;s engage with people. Make ourselves vulnerable. Take the risk, over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And be prepared to suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may make you feel like a looser, yet, would there be an option?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could Jesus do it better?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Your Influence</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/the-impact-of-your-influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/the-impact-of-your-influence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can change things to the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trust you give, the joy you share, the love you invest, the help you give, the standard you set, the problem you solve, the wisdom you share… have the potential to change things to the better, to become a blessing to you and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving people foreward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causing someone to pick up what you did and act in a similar way, and again, change things to the better, for even more people.  And in turn, cause some of them to do the same and again, change things… again and again. To the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like ripples on the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone may go further than you, causing greater change. Causing more and stronger ripples, reaching out even further. Still improving what you and others did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of those decisions and actions may have the capacity to create a movement and, as time passes by, involve hundreds or even thousands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enduring generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably, most of your influence never gets recognized in public, though. Nevertheless, it can be powerful, although you hardly ever get to know the real impact of what you did, much less can you manage its final outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret is to let go, to not expect anything back. Resisting the temptation to take control. Let others receive freely, enjoy the benefit, then pass it on freely and again, let it go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, it will go on without you, yet still because of your initiative - thanks to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still increasing your impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the benefit of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to His glory!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Really Matters - Part 3</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 06:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You are a follower of Jesus? In this case, you might be interested in the question,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What matters to Jesus?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesus himself said, it’s the glory of his Father in Heaven. To honor Him and to carry out His will. How did he do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By loving people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Jesus, this meant sharing his life and giving his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the Father is about to prepare humanity for eternity by building His universal family. And He does this in the power of His Spirit and through those who already responded to His love and follow Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a disciple of Jesus, you are an agent of Father’s love in this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you, this means sharing your life and giving your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may lift your hands and sing worship songs, you may fast and spend hours in prayer in order to honor God. That&amp;rsquo;s fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, if the outcome is not that you do His will and care for the people He wants to reach with His love, then you are just caring for your own spirituality and your own salvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t honor the Father without caring for the ones He cares for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters to Jesus? To him, this is totally clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters to you?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Really Matters - Part 2</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can thrive your career, acquire wealth and reputation, even experience tremendous impact in your ministry. Yet, if your relationships are poor&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then nothing else matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing in people is the best you can ever do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving your time and efforts or whatever you have, ultimately giving your love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love is the only currency with eternal value. And its value increases the more you give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other investment, though, love investments include risks. People can cheat you, disappoint you or just neglect you. Someone you love with all of your heart may one day turn against you and hate you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, to pin your hopes on people doesn’t seem to be quite safe, at least not in short term thinking. However, don’t get confused when your love is rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real value of your investments will finally show. If not in this life-time, then at the latest in eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesus was aware of that. He knew he could not fully rely on people, not even on his closest friends. However, in the face of suffering betrayal, hatred and torture to the fullest, he gave them everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He never gave up loving. It cost him his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, is there anything more worth living and dying for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;————&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to: &lt;a href=&#34;http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters/&#34;&gt;What really matters, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Really Matters - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/what-really-matters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most probably, it’s not the public opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not what everybody is talking about right now at the coffee table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like today’s hottest news or sensation or scandal, created by the media. Or this season’s trendiest fashion or coolest design or latest ”must have”, launched by the market. And it&amp;rsquo;s certainly not the score of last night’s soccer game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really matters is probably not whatever tries to steal your attention right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, it is what you by focusing on your life’s purpose nourish in your heart and, following your values, diligently, patiently, drip by drip, carve out as your daily walk and your path of life. By translating your purpose into daily action, here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing what is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overcoming complacency and convenience and the fear of rejection. Conquering the resistance from within you and the opinions around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidently, faithfully and joyfully pursuing what you can see as your destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you know, it’s right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Better than a Thrill</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/better-than-a-thrill2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/better-than-a-thrill2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are you looking for a thrill? Something really exciting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have been excited when you experienced the Lord for the first time, or when you got baptized in the Spirit and started speaking in tongues, or when you for the first time prayed for someone and this person actually got healed on the spot. Or maybe when you sensed the Lord’s presence during a special worship service… That, if anything, is really exciting! We may call it a thrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now the thrill is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to human nature, emotional kicks are temporary; they don&amp;rsquo;t last. That&amp;rsquo;s included in the definition of a thrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeating the same thing over and over again just isn’t that much of a thrill. You may love your work, but it probably doesn’t give you a kick every time you open the door to your office. Not like the day you entered it for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you are looking for excitement, you will have to find a fresh experience. And after that you’ll need another one, and then still another, again and again. And every time you seem to get satisfied, yet, the feeling just lasts for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, the life of a disciple of Jesus can be extraordinarily exciting, indeed. Yet, a disciple&amp;rsquo;s life is not at all about chasing excitements, not even spiritual ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, it is to faithfully continue the journey you set out on some time ago. You see the needs around you here and now with open eyes, listen to the Lord and do whatever is required. You make the necessary changes in your own life and lead others along that same path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a long time commitment, and it is put into practice day by day. Changing the world through thousands of small, persistent steps to the better. Joyfully overcoming the resistance from within you and from the outside. Making a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing something that matters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exciting is fine, yet, mattering is way more important. And still more exciting than a thrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time for a Break</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/time-for-a-break/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 06:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/time-for-a-break/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Sweden, summer has arrived and it’s time to take a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Åsa and me, this means to close down all of our regular activities and, except eating and sleeping, do other things than we usually do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what we call ”to rest”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like traveling both short and long distances to visit friends and relatives, staying for a while in Munich, my home city, hiking in the Alps and, last not least, discovering new places. This year, it’s going to be the lovely coast of Southern Croatia with world heritage Dubrovnik as our base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summer also means no blogging for a while, let’s say, until the end of August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can  still reach us, though, by mail or phone. And  you can still make an appointment, in case you would like to meet us in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to ask you for a favor. Please, would you help me evaluate my writing and make a decision concerning how to go on after the summer? You can do this by sending me a little comment. In case you don’t feel like writing a lot or don’t have the time or think that your English isn’t good enough, I allow you to keep it very short. Just write one single word into the comment box below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write either YES or NO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you write YES, this will encourage me to go on writing in about the same way as I have done so far, while your NO will encourage me to quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you so much for your response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a nice summer! Hopefully, you will hear from me again at the end of August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yours,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egmont&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Let the Sermon Fail!</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/dont-let-the-sermon-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/dont-let-the-sermon-fail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever tried to change someone’s habit without success? You kept arguing, but it just didn&amp;rsquo;t help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We probably change a habit on other grounds than logical thinking. Real change is made on a much deeper, emotional or maybe even spiritual level. It’s the level where we manage things like courage and fear, trust and distrust, faith and doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me like most of us, most of the time are not really ready for a change. Although we may not be quite happy about a certain habit, we still prefer the status quo. It just feels safer or easier; at least we know what we got and we hope that it will not get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the situation every preacher is facing. While we as the audience are nodding our heads in agreement to the sermon, our inside is already blocking the change. And for not exposing our half-heartedness, we escape into pretending. However, true preaching aims at change, changed attitudes, decisions and actions, including habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we go on listening week after week and still stay unaffected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explanation is that listening without acting leads into passive, ritualized behavior. And listening to still more sermons leads into even deeper passivity. It immunizes against the message, makes you favor the status quo and end up in self-affirmation and complacency, the perfect setting for a convenient, religious behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, listening to more sermons becomes counterproductive. It makes you feel spiritual without being it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fool ourselves when we think of having accomplished anything by just listening and agreeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, in case we are honest and willing to change, good sermons can be quite useful and inspiring. If you are ready to change, they can help you make a good decision and then act accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s up to you and me to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pamela&lt;/em&gt;
I have tried so hard to get people to see their true self so they can get the help they need from God and man and it has only resulted in futile arguments as you point out! Most people just want to talk about their problems and they will go on repeating it to anyone who would listen. The only thing that can change me or anyone is time spent alone with God &amp;hellip; unhurried time &amp;hellip;. listening to the heart of God and giving control of my life again and again back to Him so Christ can be born in me and live in me. This is a daily struggle until the surrender is total and perfection is won in Christ!! Apostle Paul is a great example to follow!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Removing the Mask</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/removing-the-mask/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/removing-the-mask/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;He was a pastor. A gifted preacher and brilliant Bible school teacher, respected and loved by his church and his large family, particularly known and appreciated for his books and seminars on family relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the unexpected happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, one day he left his wife and family, quit his ministry and moved to a far away country in order to start all over again, leaving his family, co-workers and church members behind in shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a letter, he described his desperation, revealing that he had been depressed for a longer period, feeling like a failure and even planned to take his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last three years he had been trying to keep a mask and fulfill his duty as a pastor, trying to perform whatever was expected. But now he just couldn’t do it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mask had to be removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tragic and alarming! This story may seem exceptional, at least in its final, shocking consequences. However, wearing a mask isn’t that exceptional, not among people in general, neither among believers. In fact, it seems to be a behavior particularly found in certain church cultures, practiced by common people like you and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not necessary to be a pastor in order to fall into that pit. Anyone can end up there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what could make believers and Christian workers resort to wearing a mask? And why is it so common? What can we learn from this tragedy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason seems to be fear. The fear of failing and being exposed and rejected, maybe due to a gap between a person&amp;rsquo;s abilities and the leadership position he was given and unable to fill. In order to compensate for the lack, he resorts to wearing a mask, pretending an ability or spirituality he does not possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could call it hypocrisy, yet, let me add another aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could it also be due to the gap, which the people around him produced by expecting him to be someone else than he really is? This person may be totally honest, not pretending anything, nevertheless, people identify him with the role they want him to play according to their own concept, according to how they picture him in their imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They may want to see him as the strong leader, the man of God, the apostle, the prophet or the performer of miracles, someone who makes things happen, things that satisfy their desire of affirmation and spiritual experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be rapid church growth or anything supernatural, something that gives them a sense of God’s presence, anything that produces the desired spiritual kick they might be missing in their own private lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter, whether it is a projection of people&amp;rsquo;s desires or a compensation of their own failures, a tragedy like the one described should not only be seen as one person&amp;rsquo;s, but also the people’s responsibility, as the outcome of a church environment, a hype that people bought into and cultivated, leaders as well as the ones being lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do? How can we get out of the trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, there must be an insight. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to be another spiritual super star or stage hero and there is no need for a success story. Instead, we can remind ourselves of God&amp;rsquo;s grace given once and for all times and more than enough for everyone of us. Let&amp;rsquo;s enjoy this grace and together walk the common daily walk of life in love, faith and hope, filled with gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lifting any burden of guilt and shame from each other and together enjoy our lives in God&amp;rsquo;s redemption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing our masks - becoming vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not a shame, but a first step into the freedom of an authentic life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Karin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for this very important statement! I think you are right in describing this tragic story. It is not just one person that failed and went wrong. The responsibility must be shared with the leaders. It is so important to say this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pamela&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wearing a Mask seems to be The Way of life for most Christians! If someone gets real in a prayer group for example, and tells their problem or mention they are in a crisis, the rest in the group become deathly quiet or someone makes an insane move by saying, &amp;ldquo;Oh she or he must be extra tired. Otherwise they are such wonderful people. We can pray for them.&amp;rdquo; This shuts down the person who is desperately trying to reach out for help and what God wants to do for that person in the midst of the Body of Christ before it becomes a total tragedy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How &#39;Stable&#39; Shall We Be?</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/is-your-church-stable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 06:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/is-your-church-stable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One significant characteristic of any organization is the pursuit of stability. The same is true for churches and home groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stability gives us a sense of security, peace and success. The turbulent times of initial struggles are over and we finally arrived at a place where we can lean back and enjoy our accomplishments. Now, we are established and we finally have been accepted by our surroundings. And we know how to run this church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are ”maturer”, now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From now on, all we have to do is to protect what we have got and keep growing from there. Protect it against possible agitators and trouble-makers, against know-it-alls and fault finders, and against these far too creative people and their never-ending ideas. And, last not least, against the naivety of those newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let people come in, but not up!&amp;rdquo; (Pastor of a mega church)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We really don’t want to make the same mistakes over and over again, and we&amp;rsquo;re tired of explaining everything a thousand times. Neither do we want to make any new mistakes. Why take a risk, when everything is so well settled?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the point when we get stuck in our own ways of doing things, when securing our success becomes a dominant factor and our mission locked in within the boundaries of our home made stability. This is when we give up to engage, to thrive and to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is when we close our doors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decline has begun and it’s the beginning of the end. For a while, we still enjoy the cosiness and familiarity of a well-established, stable community and the self-affirmation that comes along with it, maybe also a little hubris (”We&amp;rsquo;re a good church and way up front.”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, the average age of our group is getting alarmingly close to 70 and we don’t know what to do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution would be to start all over again. To take risks, to stretch our possibilities, to accept challenges, to explore the unknown, to humble ourselves and engage with people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give up stability - and get messy again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may loose our stability, the cosiness and familiarity of our fellowship, our comfort, complacency and respectability…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may loose it all -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but again, win souls and make disciples for Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be worth it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numbers, Numbers, Numbers!</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/numbers-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/numbers-numbers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Church leaders tend to be highly interested in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, they ask questions like, How many members does the church have, how high is the weekly attendance and how much did the offering bring? And they want to know how these numbers develop from week to week, month to month and year to year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admitted, statistics are useful. They enable us to measure and to compare, to set up goals and to stay focussed, and they make us feel successful whenever numbers go up. Numbers seem to show a church’s growth in a reliable, objective way. At least, this is what we tend to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, there is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we ever measure essential spiritual qualities like faith and love, fear of the Lord, obedience, maturity and Christlikeness, community and the power of a church’s testimony by counting numbers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we ever find out anything about the quality and the actual spiritual outcome of a church by just measuring quantities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, does the amount of hours that someone spends participating in church activities say anything about the quality of this person&amp;rsquo;s discipleship? Or can numbers about a church’s widespread popularity and numerical and financial success be translated into significant impact - in terms of fulfilling the church&amp;rsquo;s mission to make disciples?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If spiritual qualities and the actual outcome of the church are not included in our statistics, what do those statistics really say? And what do we accomplish by maximizing these numbers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the light of the church’s mission, the ultimate question for a leader and for every follower of Jesus must be, Do we really make disciples of Jesus or are we just having programs? And furthermore, do those who have been discipled, in their part, go on and make disciples? These questions are crucial, as they touch the very nerve of the church&amp;rsquo;s mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this perspective, making a handful of quality disciples may by far outweigh a thousand more names of members or attendees on our lists. After all, disciples are the kind of result that Jesus is expecting. We can&amp;rsquo;t fool him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, are we possibly fooling ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stuff or People?</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/stuff-or-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/stuff-or-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine someone handed you 10.000 USD to spend on whatever you want. The only condition would be that you had to spend it right away, on the same day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would you do with the money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe your mind would go to that fancy computer you had been eying at for a long time. Or that cool hifi-system, or the latest version of your favorite cellphone, or a diving gear for you next dream vacation, or this trendy leather jacket?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or… ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or would you rather spend the money on some event together with other people? Like financing an exotic trip or a beach vacation or a skiing adventure with your spouse or together with all of your family or some friends? Or buying toys for your kids or your grandchildren?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or could you think of just giving the money away? Like to someone you know who right now is in big trouble and needs financial help? For instance, to a young mother in your neighborhood and her children? Or to a missionary you know? Or to some charity…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what you do, your choice reveals your priorities. For yourself and for others. The ultimate question is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is really important to you? And, is it basically stuff or people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it luxury, image, prestige and short time pleasure you are interested in, or is it quality relationships and spiritual values? Will that money basically nurture your ego, or will it help you build community and bless others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, would its benefit be consumed and burned up within a short time or would it last a little longer? Would it have any significance after ten, twenty or thirty years from now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a long time perspective, stuff almost never matters, yet, people do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People always matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuff decays, relationships stay. And you can make them grow by investing in them. By giving your time and energy. And your money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, what would &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; do with the money?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honest and Joyful</title>
      <link>http://egmontmika.com/blog/honest-and-joyful/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 03:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egmontmika.com/blog/honest-and-joyful/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Meeting people is exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always exciting to listen to someone’s story. Everyone has a story worth listening to and learning from, as long as they are honest and their story is true. And it’s exciting and worth both time and effort to get engaged with people who are honest about themselves and about what they do. Free from pretending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can learn from those conversations, widen your knowledge and understanding, getting inspired. And in turn, you can encourage someone and share some of your best insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a potential to learn and to grow for both of us when we listen to each other and talk about something that is important to us, free from fear and control and manipulation and again, free from pretending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need that kind of conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need them in order to grow. And it’s a great joy to help each other along the way. That’s beautiful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, is there anything more boring than listening to gossip or constant lamenting or judging comments on others? Badly enough, you can have conversations that drain your energy and make you feel empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your conversations like? It’s very much your own choice - and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let them be honest and joyful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>